Okay, בוקר טוב Boker Tov everyone. Yeah, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. So
today's דף Daf is כ"ו Chaf-Vav 26. Before we get back to
the דף, Daf, I wanted to say something about yesterday's דף Daf
about נדרי שגגות Nidrei Shgagot and we talked about which is you
make a vow something is forbidden based on some false assumption or
you said if I did so-and-so and you thought you hadn't done
it and you had done it, and then we said it's not
binding because again you assumed it would be because you didn't intend
for it to be binding and you were working on false assumptions.
And the גמרא Gemara says the same is true by a שבועת
שגגה Shvuat Shgaga
and there are two scenarios of that. One is you said a
שבועה Shvua I won't eat this thing if such-and-such happened, which is
sort of where the גמרא Gemara moved, but the more obvious, or
the ר"ן Ran moved, the more obvious שבועת שגגה Shvuat Shgaga is
that you just take an oath to say I swear that this
did happen or that this didn't happen. And in your mind, you
really believe that that's true, but you're mistaken.
So, and that seemed to be in the גמרא Gemara also the
case of a שבועת שגגה, Shvuat Shgaga,
and then it's really fascinating because even a שבועה Shvua whose whole
point is to come and to back up your statement as being
true, it would not be that you had violated an oath, but
it would be you hadn't violated it if in your own mind
you were telling the truth. So even though you're going so far
to take a שבועה Shvua and you're wrong, it's not a שבועת
שקר Shvuat Sheker if you think you are telling the truth. Which
is funny because why don't we just say, you know, you should
have been more careful about clarifying what the truth of the matter
was before you went ahead and took a שבועה? Shvua? But nevertheless,
if you believe you're telling the truth, according to the simple read
of the גמרא, Gemara, it's not a שבועת שגגה, Shvuat Shgaga, and
that actually is how רמב"ם Rambam rules. And I just wanted to,
because this is so sort of surprising and shocking, I just wanted
to read to you this in רמב"ם Rambam just for one second.
רמב"ם Rambam in פרק ג' הלכות שבועות Perek Gimmel Hilchot Shvuot says
the following: שבועת
שגגות כיצד? Shvuat Shgagot Keitzad? So he talks about שבועת העדות, Shvuat
Ha'edut, so I'll skip that for a minute.
ואם שבועת שוא היא כגון שנשבע שלא ילבש תפילין ולא ידע שהתפילין
מצוה. Ve'im Shvuat Shav Hi Kegon Shenishba Shelo Yilbash Tefillin Velo Yada
Shehatefillin Mitzva. All right, that's one thing.
ואם שבועת שקר היא כגון שנשבע שלא אכל ונזכר שאכל או שנשבע
שלא יאכל—now
Ve'im Shvuat Sheker Hi
Kegon Shenishba Shelo Achal Venizkar She'achal O Shenishba Shelo Yochal look at
this, even if it's future oriented, you swear you won't eat, ושכח
ואכל, Veshachach Ve'achal, and you forgot about your שבועה Shvua and accidentally
you ate. Now we would say that is a classic example of
doing an עבירה בשוגג. Aveira B'shogeg. You took an oath, you did—nevertheless,
that's, you're totally פטור, Patur, that's a שבועת שגגה Shvuat Shgaga that
you're פטור Patur on because you did not willfully violate the שבועה.
Shvua. So wait a minute, if the only way a שבועת שגגה—you're
Shvuat Shgaga חייב Chayav for a שבועה Shvua is if you know
you're not telling the truth and you swear falsely, or you swear
not to do something and you consciously remember it and violate it,
then you'll never have a שוגג; Shogeg; you'll always have a מזיד.
Meizid. Because all of these, says the רמב"ם, Rambam, is a שבועת
שגגה Shvuat Shgaga that you're totally פטור Patur on. אם כן, Im
Kein, says the רמב"ם, Rambam, איזו היא שבועת שגגות ביטוי שחייבין עליה
קרבן עולה ויורד לשוא? Eizo Hi Shvuat Shgagot Bituy Shechayavin Aleha Korban
Oleh V'yored Lishava?
What's the case of a שבועת שגגה Shvuat Shgaga that you're חייב
Chayav a קרבן, Korban, that you really do transgress, right, as opposed
to this where you're saying you didn't transgress because you thought you
were telling the truth? כגון שנשבע שלא אכל והוא ידע שאכל, Kegon
Shenishba Shelo Achal Vehu Yada She'achal, you swore you didn't eat, you
knew you ate, ושבועת שקר זו שנשבע אסורה, V'sheshvuat Sheker Zo Shenishba
Asura,
and you knew it was forbidden to swear falsely. So where was
your שוגג? Shogeg? אבל לא ידע שחייבין עליה
קרבן, זו היא שבועת שגגה שחייב קרבן עולה ויורד.
Aval Lo Yada Shechayavin Aleha Korban. Zo Hi
Shvuat Shgaga Shechayav Korban Oleh V'yored. So the only שגגה... Shgaga... now
if you didn't know it was אסור, Assur, you probably would be
חייב Chayav in terms of סתם שוגג Stam Shogeg but not for
חיוב קרבן. Chiyuv Korban. Okay, and he goes on and on. So
it's quite fascinating that even a שבועה Shvua whose whole point is
to back up a statement, right, and say this statement is really
true, I so believe it I'm going to take an oath, right,
and if you are mistaken in your assumptions, you did not transgress
בשוגג, Beshogeg, you didn't transgress at all. Yes?
So, the "didn't transgress at all"—when he says פטור, Patur, does he
mean פטור אבל אסור? Patur Aval Assur?
Does he actually mean—yeah, I mean the language of the גמרא Gemara
is מותרות. Mutarot. I mean, although מותרות Mutarot refers to the food
that you swore you wouldn't eat, yeah, but it seems like it's
fundamentally not considered a violation. All right, so that's one point and
again quite fascinating when applied to שגגה. Shgaga. Now back to the
focus that we've been dealing with:
we're now focused on the principle of נדר שהותר מקצתו הותר כולו.
Neder Shehutir Miktzato Hutir Kulo. Somebody sees a lot of people eating
from his trees and he
says קונם אתם אסור לכם Konam Atem Assur Lachem and then realizes
that his father is among them. So that's a נדר שגגה Neder
Shgaga in the sense that had he known that his father was
there, he would not have included his father. So the principle of
נדר שגגה Neder Shgaga is that the father is not included in
the נדר. Neder. But fine, that's point number one: the father isn't
included because he wouldn't have wanted to have included the father had
he known. But the question number two is: what happens to the
rest of the people? Okay? And there is the debate in our
משנה Mishna between בית שמאי Beit Shammai and בית הלל. Beit Hillel.
בית שמאי Beit Shammai says the rest of the people— remain forbidden
and בית הלל Beis Hillel says permissible. And the גמרא Gemara says
that this is similar, you know, let's I guess let's just pick
it up again, we'll go back a few lines, but just it'll
be quicker to read it than to summarize it so from the
two dots in the middle of כה עמוד ב. Kaf Hei Amud
Beis. Let's just catch up a bit. רמי ואזיל. Rami v'azil. תנן
התם. Tnan hasam. פותחין בשבתות וביום טוב. Potchin b'Shabbosos u'v'Yom Tov.
Somebody took an oath or נדר, Neder, excuse me, that wine would
always be forbidden to him. You say, well, had you stopped to
think about the fact that you would it would prevent you from
eating it on שבת Shabbos drinking it on שבת Shabbos and יום
טוב? Yom Tov? And he said no, טאקי taki I hadn't thought
that through. So then okay, so then you're released from at least
the שבת Shabbos and יום טוב Yom Tov part. בראשונה היו
אומרים אותם הימים מותרין ושאר כל הימים אסורין. Ba'rishona hayu omrim osam
hayamim mutarin v'sha'ar kol hayamim asurin. That's the only part you're released
from. עד שבא רבי עקיבא ולימד נדר שהותר מקצתו הותר כולו. Ad
sheba Rabbi Akiva v'limed Neder she'hutar miktzaso hutar kulo. It's totally released.
Okay. So now we're trying to figure out the parameters of the
debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and the חכמים Chachamim and then
how you know that might translate back again into our משנה Mishna
about the father and so on. אמר רבה, Amar Rabba, said Rabba,
דכולי עלמא כל היכא דאמר אילו הייתי יודע שאבא ביניכם. d'chulei alma
kol heicha d'amar ilu hayisi yodeia she'aba beineichem. So now we're going
to actually we're going to put רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and the
חכמים Chachamim aside for a second and look at, I'm sorry, look
at the משנה Mishna בית שמאי Beis Shammai בית הלל, Beis Hillel,
that debate. So everybody agrees that had the person said, had I
known that father was among you, הייתי אומר כולכם אסורין חוץ מאבא,
hayisi omer kulchem asurin chutz me'abba, I would have added a qualifier,
I would have said I would have said everybody except for dad.
דכולן אסורין ואביו מותר. D'chulan asurin v'aviv mutar. Everybody agrees that therefore
the fundamental נדר Neder you made is not fundamentally uprooted because you
wouldn't have basically changed the נדר Neder you made, you just would
have added a qualifier, right? You would have said it's everybody but
I would have just had a qualifier except for dad. So therefore
the fundamental נדר Neder would have remained the same and therefore the
only one that gets excepted is the father. Okay, even בית הלל
Beis Hillel would agree. לא נחלקו אלא באומר אילו הייתי יודע שאבא
ביניכם הייתי אומר פלוני ופלוני אסורין ואבא מותר. Lo nechleku ela b'omer
ilu hayisi yodeia she'aba beineichem hayisi omer ploni u'ploni asurin v'abba mutar.
What they debate is when the guy said oh wait a minute,
had I realized that father was there, I never would have said
all of you, I never would have wanted for a second to
make it sound like I was forbidding it on my father before
I got to that qualifier at the end. So I would have
made a fundamentally different נדר. Neder. I would have said this is
אסור assur on you three guys on the list, but not on
you know and not on dad or whatever, but you three guys
on the list. I would have said it a fundamentally different נדר.
Neder. In that case do we say therefore the first נדר Neder
that I said is completely you know void because I never would
have said those words? I would not have said them with a
qualifier, I never would have said those words. That's the debate of
בית הלל Beis Hillel בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, okay? So here, yeah
I know I have but I'll just write it again because it
got a little whatever. So if you basically here the person said,
right, כולכם אסורין. kulchem asurin. That's what the guy said. So now
what would he have said? Okay? So if he would have said
כולכם אסורין
חוץ
מאבא,
kulchem asurin
chutz me'abba,
okay?
Or would he have said a very different statement, פלוני ופלוני? ploni
u'ploni? Okay?
So by the way if you want terminology, the רן Ran calls
this, so I would call this like this is adding a qualifier,
okay? The רן Ran calls this מקיים דבריו. mekayem devarav. You're basically
keeping your original statement you're just adding something, okay? And this is
you know completely a new statement, right? So that's I think he
calls it משנה דבריו, meshane devarav, exactly.
אמר רבה, Amar Rabba, said Rabba, דכולי עלמא, d'chulei alma, and
we're going to have רבה Rabba and רבא, Rava, okay? So רבה
Rabba says had you basically just added a qualifier you basically kept
it, everybody would have said אסור, assur, okay? Because you basically, I
mean obviously חוץ מאבא, chutz me'abba, except for father, okay? Because you
just it basically your basic first נדר Neder is still around, okay?
The only point is if you basically would have like wanted to
have made a completely different vow. So in that's where the debate
of בית הלל Beis Hillel בית שמאי Beis Shammai where
בית הלל Beis Hillel says כולכם מותרים, kulchem mutarin, everyone's permissible, and
בית שמאי Beis Shammai still says no, only father, רק אבא, rak
abba, right? But that's the debate because it was fundamentally a different
statement. רבא אמר, Rava amar, said Rava, דכולי עלמא כל היכא דאמר
אילו הייתי יודע שאבא ביניכם הייתי אומר פלוני ופלוני אסורין ואבא מותר.
d'chulei alma kol heicha d'amar ilu hayisi yodeia she'aba beineichem hayisi omer
ploni u'ploni asurin v'abba mutar.
Had you fundamentally said I would have made a completely different statement,
כולם מותרין. kulam mutarin. Everybody would have agreed, even בית שמאי, Beis
Shammai, that that of course the whole thing is in the garbage
can. לא נחלקו אלא באומר אילו הייתי יודע שאבא ביניכם הייתי אומר
כולם אסורין חוץ מאבא. Lo nechleku ela b'omer ilu hayisi yodeia she'aba
beineichem hayisi omer kulam asurin chutz me'abba.
The whole debate of בית הלל Beis Hillel בית שמאי Beis Shammai
is if you would have added just a qualifier. בית שמאי סבר
לא. Beis Shammai savar lo. Now okay so he just basically takes
the same hierarchy but no he does not switch the hierarchy, he
does not switch it, he just says that the debate is one
step further meaning or meaning he's just more מיקל. meikel. He says
if it's a if you would have made a completely different statement
every Everybody would have said מותר mutar *muttar*. Okay, this is obviously
more מותר mutar. *muttar*, it's fundamentally is a different statement. If you
would have made a different statement had you known, and then everybody
agrees that the first statement is void, even בית שמאי *Beis Shammai*.
בית הלל *Beis Hillel* goes so far to say that even if
you would have just added a qualifier, right, still the whole original
נדר neder *neder* is void. In this case of just a qualifier
here בית הלל *Beis Hillel* says void, and בית שמאי *Beis Shammai*
says no, it's still רק אבא *rak Abba* is מותר mutar *muttar*.
Okay, so here, I'll write מותר mutar *muttar* rather than void. Okay,
so the bottom line what it boils down to is, here's the
takeaway. רבא Rava *Rava* says, let's ignore בית שמאי *Beis Shammai* because
we פוסקן *pasken* like בית הלל *Beis Hillel*. רבא Rava. *Rava* says
when is it void? It's void when you are only when you
are משנה Mishnah *meshane*. Okay, משנה דבריו meshane devarav *meshane devarav*. Only
if according to בית הלל *Beis Hillel* it's only void only if
you basically would have said a completely different statement. Whereas רבא Rava
*Rava* says, no, according to בית הלל *Beis Hillel*, it's void even
if you are מקיים דבריו mekayam d'varav. *mekayem devarav*. Okay, even if
you just add a qualifier, even if you were to have just
added a qualifier, that is enough to say you would not have
said exactly what you said originally and therefore that's enough to void
it. We'll just do one more sentence and then we'll take Rabbi
Dov's question. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. Okay, it conceptualizes
this debate with the debate of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir*
and רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*. Or so the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says like this: בית שמאי *Beis Shammai* סבר לה *savar lah*
כרבי מאיר *keRabbi Meir* דאמר *de'amar* תפוס לשון ראשון rishon, *tfos lashon
rishon*, ובית הלל *uBeis Hillel* סבר לה *savar lah* כרבי יוסי *keRabbi
Yose*, excuse me רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir. *Rabbi Meir* and רבי יוסי
*Rabbi Yose*, דאמר *de'amar* בגמר דבריו אדם נתפס *begmar devarav adam nitfas*.
So here's a classic debate of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir*
and רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yose*. A person says by an animal, הרי
זו תמורת עולה תמורת שלמים *harei zo tmurat olah tmurat shelamim*. Now
an animal cannot both be an עולה *olah* and a שלמים *shelamim*,
okay, a normal animal. So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir, *Rabbi Meir* says
the first... you said תמורת עולה *tmurat olah*, that made it an
עולה *olah*, what you said at the end is irrelevant, okay, so
that's בתחילת דבריו אדם נתפס *bit'chilas devarav adam nitfas*, okay, תפוס לשון
ראשון rishon *tfos lashon rishon*, excuse me. רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yose* says
no, בגמר דבריו אדם נתפס *begmar devarav adam nitfas*. You can't finish
a statement... you can't, you know, chop a statement in the middle,
you have to hear the end, and you include the end in
it and somehow this animal becomes a hybrid. Okay, so how is
that relevant here? So it's relevant here because the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
is saying is if this would have fundamentally been the same statement
and you just would have added a qualifier, then בית הלל *Beis
Hillel* is... then בית שמאי *Beis Shammai* is saying then you really
fundamentally have still kept your same נדר neder. *neder*. It's basically the
same נדר neder *neder*, there's a little qualifier but that doesn't change
the basic identity of the statement. The basic statement is the same
statement, so therefore, therefore yes אבא *Abba* is excluded but fundamentally the
נדר neder, *neder* is still in place. And בית הלל *Beis Hillel*
says no, you look... you can't end a statement in the middle,
okay, you look at the whole statement, the effect of the whole
statement is a different statement even though the beginning is the same
it's a different statement and therefore the whole original one is void.
Yes Dov you had a question.
I have a short technical question and a conceptual one. The short
technical one is if I say like my figs are אסור asur?
*assur* to all those people over there, do those people have to
hear me say that? That's just a technical thing about a נדר
neder, *neder*.
Well if they don't hear me say it they're נדרי אונסים *nidrei
onsim* which we're going to get to in a minute, but you
know
yeah, it's still a נדר neder *neder*.
Okay good and
conceptually to the language I say אומר פלוני ופלוני אסורים ואבא מותר
mutar, *Omer ploni u'ploni assurim ve'Abba muttar*. Why do I need the
אבא מותר mutar, *Abba muttar*? If I specify פלוני ופלוני *ploni u'ploni*
it's not ploni. Yeah you wouldn't, yeah you wouldn't.
I mean you wouldn't, you wouldn't. I mean it's just a thing,
look, I don't know, it's saying that like really if you had
a group of people and you want to say it's אסור asur
*assur* to them and your father was there, you wouldn't have felt
the need to... halachically you're right, you wouldn't have felt the psychological
need to have clarified that you're excluding אבא מותר mutar *Abba muttar*.
I think so, like I got my dad and Abe and Yoni.
I said it's אסור asur *assur* to Abe and Yoni. I wouldn't
feel the need...
Halachically you're right. All right. Now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* goes on.
You must be an איש ההלכה *ish ha-halacha*, okay, yeah. Just a
thought pressing on me, is
this whole thing that you're looking for a פתח *pesach*, right? I
mean he's already made this נדר neder *neder* and they're going back
to him and saying and he's saying oh you see your dad...
If I had known I would have added a qualifier from the
get-go.
Right, but I want to clarify, it's not necessarily a פתח *pesach*.
In the case where
they do have to ask him and clarify, but it's not necessarily
a התרת נדר *hataras neder* by פתח *pesach*. When he says oh
I thought I didn't realize it was my dad, then that's a
mistaken assumption and that's נדרי שגגות *nidrei shegagos*. נדרי שגגות *nidrei shegagos*
don't need התרת נדרים *hataras nedarim*. Okay, they just automatically, once we
clarify that we say okay then it wasn't binding for your dad.
Right the case about שבתות וימים טובים *Shabassos veYomim Tovim* by the
wine, there it's like I knew all the facts, I just didn't
think the issues through. There you needed התרת נדר *hataras neder*. But
you are right that you have to... I wouldn't call it a
פתח *pesach*, but you have to go back and clarify, right, that...
and you have to ask him. Oh, wait wait I didn't realize
my dad was there. Okay fine, but let me ask you a
question, like what would you have said had you known otherwise? Right,
we have to have that follow-up question. But it's important to know
that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* when it looks at the case of
the wine. And that's the case where you need a התרת נדר
*hatarat neder*, because that case the guy knew the facts, he didn't
think them through. And when we look at the case of the
אבא *abba*, he didn't need a התרת נדר *hatarat neder*, it just
wasn't binding by אבא *abba*. But they're parallel because one way or
another the initial... the נדר *neder* was made doesn't apply to a
certain segment of it. And then the question is what impact that
has on the rest. And now what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* saying
between רבה Rabbah *Rabbah* and רבא Rava, *Rava* is—and this is surprising—we're
only going to know the impact based on the hypothetical, based at
asking the guy, what would you have said. And that we should
stop and point out is a little bizarre. Like, who the heck
cares what I would have said? I didn't say it. So the
question should be, given the נדר *neder* as it was said, what
is the impact of removing part of it? Right? And that we're
going to get to in a minute. But like, what I would
have said otherwise, how that affects whether right now... the question we
should have asked is: right now, if we look at this group
of people as a like coherent group and the נדר *neder* as
like a single unit, then when you remove it from one, the
whole thing falls apart. If you look at it as like ten
people and I remove one—meaning here actually we're going to see this
in a minute—this is really what we should have said, not hypothetically
what I would have said would have mattered, but the following. If
I said, "All of you are אסור asur. *assur*," and it turns
out, "Oh, I didn't realize Charlie was there, I like Charlie." So
then okay, that was a single unit and it all falls away.
But if I said, "You, you, you, you, you, and you are
אסור asur *assur*," and then it turns out that Charlie... I didn't
realize I was talking about Charlie, then maybe I see that that's
not one coherent unit. That's six different things and then Charlie can
go away and the whole נדר *neder* isn't seen of as a
coherent unit. That's looking at what is the quality, the nature of
the נדר *neder* itself, right? Whereas here the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* is
asking like hypothetically what would I have said impacts how much I
think that this is, you know, that this is fundamentally a wrong
נדר *neder* or not. So yes, it is interesting that you have
to ask that follow-up question and we care about the hypothetical. Yes.
Yeah, it could be... in other words, like the whole thing is
about the power of language and its binding nature. So at a
certain point what the גמרא gemara *Gemara* is considering, it seems to
me, is: wait a second, let's loosen up the binding nature and
go back into his thought. In other words, there's an intrinsic relationship
between your thought, the facts on the ground, and your language. Ah,
you thought that you said it like it's already, it's קיים *kayam*.
I'm going to go back into your mind and have you reassess...
I guess so.
Right, and that's true, meaning the reason you need the thought is
פיו ולבו שוין *piv velibbo
shavin*. But the idea of הותר מקצתו הותר כולו hutar miktzato hutar
kulo. *hutar miktzato hutar kullo* is because in your mind you would
have had theoretical... hypothetically you'd have other words in your mind, and
that creates a bigger detach from the words you said. It's a
little bizarre. Okay, once you said it, presumably we would deal with
the effect of it out there and what is the quality of
what you had said. Yeah, one last question and we'll move on.
Is the נפקא מינה *nafka mina* is that we're going back into
his mind, asking what his intention was, and then coming up with
a formulation that should be used in the סייפא *seifa*?
Exactly, exactly, which is quite strange. Yeah, exactly. So let's take a
look, because the next move the גמרא gemara *Gemara* moves, which is
not בית הלל *Beit Hillel* ובית שמאי *ve-Beit Shammai* but the רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* case,
is a position which I feel would have like just made a
little, you know, made more sense. So, and we'll see how the
גמרא gemara *Gemara* deals with it. Let's take a look. איתיביה רב
פפא לרבא l'Rava. *Eitiveih Rav Pappa le-Rava*. So רב פפא *Rav Pappa*
asked רבא Rava. *Rava*, who says, now again, the basic thing to
remember about רבא Rava *Rava* is he says that even if it
just would have been a qualifier, that would have been enough for
the whole thing to fall off. Okay, רבא Rava, *Rava*. כיצד keitzad?
אמר רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva. *Keitzad amar Rabbi Akiva*. So here we've
got a משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* that says: in what way did רבי
עקיבא Rebbe Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* say... this is the משנה Mishnah, *Mishnah*
about the case of the wine and שבתות וימים טובים *Shabbatot ve-Yamim
Tovim*. כיצד אמר רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva נדר שהותר מקצתו הותר כולו
neder shehutar miktzato hutar kulo. *Keitzad amar Rabbi Akiva neder she-hutar miktzato
hutar kullo*. What would be like another application of this principle? Somebody
said, "קונם שאיני נהנה לכולכם lekulchem *Konam she-eini neheneh le-kulkhem*." קונם *Konam*
that, you know, my stuff is forbidden to all of you guys.
הותר אחד echad. מהן הותר כולן *Hutar echad me-hen hutar kulla-m*. That's
a single unified נדר *neder*, because all of you are one single
group, and if it turns out that one it doesn't apply to
one of you, either through a התרת נדרים *hatarat nedarim* or through
נדרי שגגות *nidrei shegagot* or for whatever reason the נדר *neder* is
no... winds up not being binding by one of you, then it's
not binding by any because you're all a unified group. Let's say
instead I said, "שאיני נהנה לא לזה ולא לזה ולא לזה *she-eini
neheneh lo le-zeh velo le-zeh velo le-zeh*." Okay, not you, not you,
not you. הותר הראשון הותרו כולם kulam *Hutar ha-rishon hutru kullam*. Then
it matters. הותר הראשון הותרו כולם, kulam, הותר האחרון האחרון מותר mutar
וכולם אסורים *Hutar ha-rishon hutru kullam, hutar ha-acharon ha-acharon muttar ve-kullam asurim*.
If the first guy is... was הותר *hutar* because I again didn't
intend it, it was שגגות *shegagot* or I got a היתר *heter*,
whatever, then it goes off for all of them. If it was
the last guy, then it only goes off for the last
guy and the rest are אסורים *asurim*.
And of course the middle guy, we're going to see later, it
goes from the middle guy towards the end. Now what's the logic
here? So before we get to logic, let's just say simply I
would have said... let's not say לא לזה ולא לזה *lo le-zeh
velo le-zeh*. Let's say I just would have said: נדר *neder* that
this is אסור assur? *assur* to Michael and to Charlie and to
David and, you know, to Joe there and to Jonathan Dove and
David. And I'm sorry, and חיים *Chaim*. I don't want to leave
you out. And חיים *Chaim*. And then it turns out that oh,
wait a minute, wait a minute, I thought we were talking about
a different David. I would never want my good
friend... one thing about you, one thing about you, one thing about
you. If you remove one person, it doesn't affect, right, doesn't affect
anybody else. Here's it's a little different. I said not you, nor
you, nor you, nor you, nor you, nor you, nor you, nor
you. So the גמרא gemara sort of seeing this as everybody is
hinged, it's like it's applying what I said to you, let's say
I said and, not it's forbidden to you, and you, and you,
and you. So it's taking your state and applying it down and
it's like making it a chain. So here's the best example I
can think of. You ever have a case in, sorry for the
nerdy example, in Microsoft Excel, if you have linked-up cells, you know,
and one cell is like based on like the previous one plus
something or whatever, and you take out one of them in the
middle, then everything below says like it's missing the reference. Everything else
becomes void because it's all based on its reference, you know what
I'm saying? Anyway, fine. Okay, so that seems to be the assumption
here, okay, that since I'm applying it, when I remove one link,
it affects everything lower in the link.
But this לו לזה lo leze would change everything.
So it would make sense as to say לו לזה, lo leze,
right, it might make sense in how you say it, לו לזה
ולו לזה lo leze velo leze or whatever or לו לזה lo
leze period if you had the ו vav or not the ו.
vav. לו לזה, לו לזה, לו לזה. lo leze, lo leze, lo
leze. If you didn't have the ו, vav, presumably they would all
be independent. If you had the ו, vav, maybe you're just saying
applying it down. So this is a great משנה Mishnah, because this
basically says I don't care what hypothetically you would have said, I
care what you did say, and to what degree is that נדר
that you did say, is it one coherent whole or is it
a collection of multiple individual units? Or the third possibility, it's a
chain. Okay, and then when you remove one piece of it does
it affect the rest or not? Okay, the גמרא gemara now is
going to try to fit this in somehow to the debate of
רבא Rava and רבה Rabbah. about what I would have said. And
I gotta tell you, the next six lines of the גמרא Gemara
are very, very
confusing. You try to make sense out of it, I'm going to
do my best, let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this: Okay, בשלמא לרבה, מוקים לה לרישא דאמר לזה לזה, וסיפא
דאמר לכולכם.
Bishlama leRabbah, mokim la
lereisha de’amar laze laze, veseifa de’amar lekulchem.
I get רבה. Rabbah רבה Raba would have said in the beginning
it's a לזה לזה laze laze case, and in the end it's
a לכולכם lechulchem case. What the heck does that mean? So here's
going to be my interpretation. It's not exactly what the ר"ן Ran
says, but it's the best I can do. Okay, so the cases
in the משנה Mishnah were, right, remember, here's the case in the
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva משנה, Mishnah. right? One was if it
says כולכם אסורין, kulchem assurim, והותר אחד מהן, vehuttar echad mehen, then
it says מותר mutar for everyone, right? That's the case in the
משנה, mishnah, right? Because you remove one piece, it all falls away.
Right? If you say, right, לו לזה ולו לזה, lo leze velo
leze,
right, then what does it say? Then it says whatever, okay, the
question about the גרסא, girsa, then it says in that case if
it's
ראשון, כולם מותרים, kulam mutarim,
right, כולם whatever, מותרים. mutarim. And if it's אחרון, acharon, then it's
only
אחרון acharon מותר.
mutar Okay. How's the first one, כולכם אסורין, kulchem assurim, how's that
become...
No, and then והותר לאחד מהן. vehuttar leechad mehen. Then it was
והותר לאחד. vehuttar leechad. Okay, so if it was you said כולכם
אסורין, kulchem assurim,
okay, you said כולכם אסורין kulchem assurim and it became מותר mutar.
for one, then they all become מותר mutar? because you removed one,
it's all one unit. Right? If you said לו לזה ולו לזה
lo leze velo leze and you removed one, if you removed the
first one, the idea of the chain, this is what the inherent
logic of the משנה mishnah is, then they all fall off. If
you removed the last, you've only removed the last. Okay, that's the
משנה. mishna Now, here's how the גמרא Gemara is interpreting it, because
the גמרא Gemara doesn't care about chain or unit or collection. The
גמרא Gemara cares about what you would have said. Okay, so for
כולכם אסורין kulchem assurim to become מותר, mutar right, which you removed
one, it only would have been if you would have said something
fundamentally different. So what would you have said what would you have
had to have said that would have been fundamentally different rather than
כולכם אסורין? kulchem assurim? You would have had to say לו לזה.
lo leze.
This is what you would have said. Would have, according to the
גמרא. Gemara So in order to get to the conclusion, in order
to get to the conclusion of כולכם מותרים, kulchem mutarim, if you
need it to be משנה דברים, mishneh devarim, if you need it
to be a radical change in order to be everybody מותר, muttar.
so in order to get from כולכם אסורין kulchem assurim to כולכם
מותרים kulchem mutarim it would have been only if you would have
said לו לזה. lo leze. Now, to get from לו לזה ולו
לזה lo leze velo leze to כולכם מותרים, kulchem mutarim, what would
it have been? It would have also had to be a radical
change. What would have been a radical change? If
instead of saying not you, not you, not you, not you, if
I would have said oh, had I known I would have just
said not you, not you and not you, so that's still a
מקיים דברים, mekayem devarim, that would have only removed one person. So
if we want to say that what... makes it completely מותר muttar.
is I would have said something completely different, so instead of saying
not you, not you, not you, not you, oh, had I realized
Joe was there, I wouldn't have, I just would have said none
of you except Joe. I don't know why that would have been
a preferable thing, but anyway, so the only way you're going to
get with a משנה דבריו m'shaneh d'varav, to go from this to
כולם מותרים kulam mutarim is if you say
כולכם. kulchem. Okay.
It's a little, it's bizarre,
but
כולם, כולכם חוץ
מ,
kulchem
chutz
me, כולם חוץ
מ, kulam chutz me, חוץ מ chutz me אחד.
I know, it's in the reverse, in the reverse.
So make a difference if you said except from my father everyone
is...
maybe, but I don't want to go there. Okay. So רבה Raba
is saying we got a משנה, mishna we got a beautiful משנה
mishna. that doesn't care about what hypothetically you would have said, just
cares about the nature of the נדר. But now we're trying to
force it into this model of well, what would you have said,
that's what really matters. So רבה Raba says well according to רבה
Rabba? we got it. Here the reason everybody's מותר muttar. is because
it's a case where you would have said something completely different. לא
זה ולא זה. lo ze velo ze. Here the לא זה lo
ze where it's מותר muttar is because he also would have said
something completely different. You would have said כולכם, kulchem, okay, חוץ מ.
chutz me. That's how it would have worked. So let's just read
that. בשלמא לרבא מוקימנא לרישא דאמר לא זה ולא זה bishlama lerava
mokimna lereisha de'amar lo ze velo ze
meaning you would have said לא זה ולא זה lo ze velo
ze וסיפא דאמר לכולכם veseifa de'amar lechulchem
and you would have said לכולכם lechulchem and that's why it's מותרים.
mutarim. אלא לדידך ela ledidach
according to you that even a qualifier would have been enough to
completely undermine it, okay, so how would it have made sense? בשלמא
דרישא מוקימנא דאמר לכולכם. bishlama dereisha mokimna de'amar lechulchem.
So the רישא, reisha, so this is according to whatever, so now
let's deal how it would have been for רבא. Rava The רישא
reisha it would have been enough to say לכולכם l'kulchem because remember
for him a qualifier is enough if you would have said לכולכם
חוץ, lechulchem chutz, right? That also would be enough of a change.
Even a qualifier is enough of a change. Yes? So that would
have got you to כולם מותרים. kulam mutarim. Okay, אלא ela here's
the problem. Why should it be a problem? סיפא דאמר לא זה
ולא זה seifa de'amar lo ze velo ze רבי עקיבא היא. Rabbi
Akiva hi. So it's for the סיפא seifa here לא זה ולא
זה ולא זה lo ze velo ze velo ze לא זה ולא
זה lo ze velo ze whatever, either way,
same point. Anyway, same point, so what would have been for רבא
Rava by analogy? It would have been enough to have been מותר
mutar. if you were to have said right לא זה ולא זה
lo ze velo ze and you wouldn't have included like the third
person the other person. A little bit of a change, right? רבא,
Rava רבא. Rava, Even a little bit of a change here would
have been enough to be כולכם מותרים, kulchem mutarim, right? All right,
still no problem. Big deal. All right fine, to get to כולכם
מותרים kulchem mutarim a qualifier would have been enough. You wouldn't have
needed a major change. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, so that's
רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva אמאי פליגי רבנן עליה? amai peligi rabanan alei?
Why do the רבנן rabanan argue? ואמרת דברי הכל מותר. ve'amarta divrei
hakol mutar.
You said that everybody says that when you fundamentally change it, it's
מותר. mutar. Now what do you mean fundamentally change it? You just
said that you would have said לא זה ולא זה lo ze
velo ze and here you would have said לא זה ולא זה.
lo ze velo ze. Why would you have like fundamentally changed it?
Okay, right? I mean why should this be a case that everybody
says it's מותר? mutar. So here's what I think, again, I really
don't know, I mean I could tell you the long run, okay,
this גמרא Gemara is very, very hard to explain. Here's what I
would suggest, that what the גמרא Gemara is saying is, is that
if you say,
what would I have said?
Hold on. This did make sense when I tried to figure it
out or at least some semblance of sense. Why is it that
everybody says it's מותר mutar because...
Yeah,
I think what it's saying is that in the case of
כולכם חוץ, kulchem chutz, חוץ chutz is a modifier, right? Or a
qualifier, I should say qualifier, right? Okay, it limits the scope of
כולכם. kulchem. But if I say, if I compare these two
sentences: לא לראובן, lo leReuven,
let's just do ראובן, Reuven, ולא לשמעון velo leShimon or לשמעון, leShimon,
I don't know we could do the remove the לא'ס. lo's. לראובן
לשמעון וללוי. leReuven leShimon uleLevi. That's statement number one. And statement number
two was
לראובן ולשמעון. leReuven uleShimon.
Is that statement a qualifier of the previous statement? No. It's not
taking it and qualifying it. It's a smaller statement, but it's a
different statement. It's not a qualifier. Okay, so I understand that this
is what again, if you're confused, it's not just you, okay. The
גמרא Gemara is very difficult, but I understand what the גמרא Gemara
is saying is like this. According to me the reason I could
get to כולם מותרים kulam mutarim רבא Rava, is I could say
what you would have said would have been radically different and therefore
you could have got to כולם מותרים. kulam mutarim. But according to
you the חידוש chiddush of this position is even with a little
bit of a qualifier. So I get from here it could have
been כולם מותרים kulam mutarim if you would have added a little
qualifier. But from here to change לא זה ולא זה lo ze
velo ze you're not going to get a qualifier. It'll either be
כולכם חוץ kulchem chutz or it'll be a shorter לא זה ולא
זה lo ze velo ze but either way it's not a qualifier
and if it's not a
qualifier... Because the חכמים Chachamim would only disagree if it was basically
the same statement with a qualifier. But once it was a different
statement, according to רבא, Rava. even the חכמים Chachamim agree. Okay? So
therefore he's saying that this is the way I'm reading it. That
the difference between ראובן שמעון ולוי Reuven Shimon v'Levi and ראובן שמעון
Reuven Shimon is not the same statement with a qualifier. It's a
different statement. So according to you, why is that only a רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva position?
Is it something that maybe when you shorten the statement, maybe they're
conceptualizing it as that everything
is dependent on
the last element?
I understand. Let's move on, okay? We've done with this גמרא Gemara
the best I can do. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
ואמר ליה רבא, V'amar lei Rava, so רבא Rava says, ולרבה לרבי
עקיבא מי ניחא, U'leRabba leRebbe Akiva mi nicha, one minute. How does
this work even according to רבה? Rabba, That you're saying, again, you're
saying the move from this part to this part is because hypothetically
you would have said something significantly different. You would have been משנה
דיבורא. meshaneh dibura. Okay? מי ניחא. Mi nicha.
סיפא במאי אוקימתא דאמר לכולכם. Seifa bemai okimta d'amar l'kulchem. So the
סיפא seifa is you said לזה ולזה lazeh velazeh and you're saying
you would have said לכולכם l'kulchem and that makes it מותר. mutar
That's how we said it according to רבה, Rabba. right? It's all
about hypothetically what you would have said. So he says, one minute.
האי דין הוא ראשון והאי דין הוא אחרון. Hai dein hu rishon
vehai dein hu acharon. What do you mean the first and the
last according to you? And why what does it mean oh, if
it was the first guy, then it's all מותר. mutar The last
guy, right, then it's then only the last guy is מותר. mutar.
What do first and last have to do with the fact that
hypothetically you would have said a different statement? Right? Which is basically
pointing out that this משנה mishna has nothing to do with hypothetically
what you would have said. Okay? But so that's what he's like
saying. I don't get it. According to that, this is מותר mutar.
because you hypothetically would have said a radically different statement. So what's
the distinction it makes between whether you're excluding the first guy or
the last guy? How's that relevant? One minute. So the גמרא Gemara
says, אלא, Ela, so finally it gets to what the משנה mishna,
really means. רישא דאמר לכולכם Reisha d'amar l'kulchem וסיפא כגון שתלאן זה
בזה. v'seifa kegon shetla'an zeh bazeh.
So what you did was you basically, the רישא reisha would have
been you said לכולכם and maybe then and then you excluded one
guy that would be like a חוץ מי chutz mi or whatever,
but that would have been enough to make the whole thing. But
the סיפא seifa is that you sort of made them all linked.
ואמר פלוני כפלוני ופלוני כפלוני. V'amar ploni k'ploni u'ploni k'ploni. Okay?
And therefore because it's all daisy-chained and linked, it depends where you
cut the link. דיקא נמי דתניא, Deika nami d'tanya, we saw in
a ברייתא, braita, which should be דתנן, d'tnan, הותר האמצעי, hutar ha'emtza'i,
if it was a middle guy, הימנו ולמטה מותרין, heimenu u'lemata muttarin,
then everybody below him falls off, למעלה אסורין. lemala assurim.
So basically at the end, the גמרא Gemara does not, hopefully does
not try to go fit this whole idea of hypothetically what you
would have said into that משנה. mishna It seems to basically concede
that the point of that משנה meshaneh. is not based on hypothetically
what you would have said. It's based on to what degree is
the collection of people a single unit, a collection, a collection of
units, or some type of a
chained structure. And then it depends when you move one, how it
affects the other. But that's about the nature of the נדר itself,
not about hypothetically what you would have said. But the גמרא Gemara
is not giving up. It still wants to focus that hypothetically what
you would have said matters and this debate of רבא Rava. and
רבה. Rabba. Yes.
So once we're changing the focus of the משנה, meshaneh. then it
doesn't matter whether you hold like רבא Rava or like רבה. Rabba
Right.
I mean, the גמרא Gemara never went back and said so fine,
if that's what it's about, where does the רבא Rava and רבה
Rabbah. fit in or whatever? Again, I'd like to just leave it
and move on. Okay.
Why can't we just say it doesn't fit in?
I know, but the גמרא Gemara normally wouldn't be happy. You got
to make משניות mishnayos fit in with what אמוראים Amoraim say. Yes.
Does הירושלמי Yerushalmi interpret the משנה meshaneh in this kind of a
way?
I don't know. I didn't check. Okay. So let's take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara's says like this. איתיביה רב אדא בר אהבה
לרבא. Eisivei Rav Adda bar Ahava l'Rava.
Now the next questions at least make a little bit more sense,
although again they still continue with this question of hypothetically what they
would have said. קונם בצל שאני טועם. Konam batzal she'ani to'eim. Okay?
בצל, Batzal, excuse me.
Forbidden on me is like a קרבן korban all onions that I
won't eat them. שהבצל רע ללב, Shehabatzal ra lalev, because I've heard
that onions are bad for the heart. אמרו לו, Amru lo, they
said to him, והלא הכופרי יפה ללב, vehalo haKufri yafeh lalev, one
minute, the village or whatever, it's a certain type of an onion,
כופרי, Kufri, whatever, that's good for the heart. So he said, הותר
בכופרי, Hutar beKufri, he's permitted to eat those types of onions because
he never would have, it's clear he never would have intended the
ones that are good for the heart. ולא בכופרי בלבד הותר אלא
בכל הבצלים. V'lo beKufri bilvad hutar ela bechol habetzalim. מה סבר רבי
מאיר דהתירו בכל הבצלים? Mai savar Rebbe Meir d'hatiru bechol habetzalim?
So that depends on if הותר מקצת הותר כולו. hutar miktzat hutar
kulo. Okay?
Now, מאי לאו? mai lav? So now, again, a very nice simple
statement because he made it all one big unit. So you move
one element of the unit, the whole thing falls off. Now the
גמרא Gemara's introduces the question of what hypothetically he would have said.
מאי לאו דאמר? Mai lav d'amar? It must be a case that
he said, אילו הייתי יודע שהכופרי יפה ללב, Ilu hayiti yodeia shehaKufri
yafeh lalev, had I known it was good for the heart, הייתי
אומר hayiti omer I would have said, כל הבצלים אסורין וכופרי מותר.
kol habetzalim assurim veKufri muttar. I would have said a qualifier. So
since I would have said a qualifier, therefore you see and that
would have been... enough to have said that it all falls off.
Okay, even if I just would have said it was a qualifier.
Now that should be a question to רבא, Rava. right? Because that
shows that even a qualifier is enough to make it all fall
off. So it's not clear, right? Is that clear? Meaning the גמרא
Gemara is assuming that the guy would have said all onions except
for the קופרי, kufari, which is a qualifier.
And then, and therefore it's all מותר. mutar. And it's all מותר.
mutar, So that's the position of רבא, Rava that with a qualifier
it all is מותר. mutar, It's a קל וחומר kal v'chomer question
on רבא. Rava? So the ראשונים Rishonim say that this question is
a question on not only on רבא Rava but even on רבה.
Rabbah? But how's it a question on רבה? Rabbah Because רבה Rabbah
says that actually with a qualifier it all does fall off. So
the reason it's a question on רבה Rabbah's is because we introduced
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir into the equation. And you'll remember that the
גמרא Gemara earlier said that רבה's Rabbah position is based on rejecting,
against the רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir Do you remember that? The גמרא
Gemara said רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who says תחילתו בשגגה וסופו ברצון,
techilato b'shigagah v'sofo b'ratzon, רבה Rabbah. would say סופו בשגגה. sofo b'shigagah.
So that's somehow how it also becomes a question on רבה. Rabbah
But more basically it's a question on רבא. Rava, That if you
would have said a qualifier, why does it all fall off? So
wait, let's just see what the גמרא Gemara answers. It's a very
easy answer. Who told the גמרא Gemara what he would have said?
So the גמרא Gemara says, so the גמרא Gemara says, לא באומר
אלו הייתי יודע שהקופרי יפה ללב הייתי אומר בצל פלוני ופלוני אסורים
וקופרי מותר. lo b'omer ilu hayiti yode'a she-hakufari yafeh l'lev hayiti omer
btzal ploni u-ploni asurim v'kufari mutar. No,
I would have been, I would have said a fundamentally different statement
and therefore I would have said everything, and therefore it works even
according to רבה Rabbah because it would have been a משנה דבריו,
m'shaneh d'varav. I would have said something completely different. And it works
even according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir even though רבה Rabbah would
say רבי מאיר would be more strict, this is a case where
you would have completely changed your statement and even רבי מאיר would
have agreed. רבי מאיר אליבא דרבי עקיבא aliba d'Rabbi Akiva או אליבא
דרבנן, o aliba d'rabanan, and רבי מאיר here would work you know
even according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and the רבנן Rabanan because
basically it would be a case of משנה דבריו. m'shaneh d'varav Okay,
yes. But this isn't a qualifier.
This is a another שגגה. shigagah. He...
No,
no, no, again. It's a שגגה. shigagah. It's a שגגה shigagah for
the one thing you wouldn't have wanted to do. What is its
impact on the rest? And the way we determine when you remove
that one type of onion from the נדר, what happens to the
rest of the נדר, that's the principle of הותרה מקצתה הותרה כולה.
hutrah miktzatah hutrah kullah. And the way we know does it make
the whole rest of the נדר fall off or not, the גמרא
Gemara is now saying is based on hypothetically what you would have
said had you have realized. That's what רבא Rava and רבה Rabbah
are saying, right?
Yes, but except in... I mean I hate to get bogged down
in semantics and syntax but this whole thing is semantics. Yes. He's
saying I'm not going to eat onions because they're bad for my
heart.
Right. He didn't say, he didn't say those onions that are bad
for my heart or he didn't say if they're bad for my
heart. He said because they are. Which basically means that he was
working with a mistaken assumption. And therefore and therefore...
No, no, no.
Qualifier means how, I'm referring to what his other statement would have
been. A statement with a qualifier. No, the reason that the קופרי
kufari is excluded is because it was a שגגה shigagah regarding the
קופרי. kufari. How do we determine whether all of the rest of
the onions are מותר or אסור? assur, So what רבא Rava and
רבה Rabba, are saying is the way we determine that is by
assessing what he would have said had he known. And would he
have said a completely different statement or would he have said the
same statement with a qualifier? If the word qualifier is confusing, I
can use the ר"ן's Ran's term and say would he have been
משנה דבריו m'shaneh d'varav or would he have been מקיים דבריו. mekayam
d'varav. Okay. So therefore that's, so that's the point. It's to interpret
not why are the קופרי מותר kufari mutar but what, whether it
affects the rest depends on what the nature of the other statement
would have been. So the גמרא Gemara says oh it looks presumably
it would have just been a case of a מקיים דבריו. mekayem
devarav. So then why does it all fall off? No, who tells
you, maybe it would have been a case of משנה דבריו meshaneh
devarav. and that's why it all falls off. Yes.
But doesn't it have to be the pull opposite, oh onions are
actually good for you. No, there's no evidence onions are at all
bad for you, you'd be saying the same thing, right? Ah, that
would be interesting because if somebody is anxious about it maybe he
would have wanted to cover his bases even במקום ספק. bimkom safek.
I don't know, it's a good question. Yes.
I understood you to say a few minutes ago, so the question
is whether or not all the people are being regarded as sort
of one group or is it, right?
I'm just thinking about it a little differently. What do you think
about this? I don't think the גמרא's concern is about the people.
The גמרא's concern is how it's thinking about words. Whether the words
are all seen as one... I guess thinking about words almost like
blocks of wood. Like they're... like what is... it's about language, right?
It's almost independent of... you got... you got...
I don't know if we're disagreeing. Meaning whether I look at all
of you as one big coherent unit or whether I look at
you as seven distinct individuals, it's not an existential question. The question
is how have my words grouped you together or not? So we're
saying the same thing. If I say, if I say my דף
יומי Daf Yomi class, I'm looking at you as one sort of
coherent unit, right? If I am say, if I name you, then
I'm looking at you as distinct individuals. And if I say you
and you and you, maybe I'm looking at you as a sort
of list of linked individuals. So I'm not saying that's... when I
said how we're looking at I don't mean how existentially... existentially what
the reality of this is. I mean how those words are framing
that. Okay, so the גמרא says like this.
Okay, so here's another case.
Okay. איתי Aitay רבינא Ravina לרבא. So now רבינא Ravina asks רבא.
Rava, רבי נתן אומר Rabbi Natan Omer יש נדר שמקצתו מותר ומקצתו
אסור. yesh neder shemikztato mutar umiktzato asur. There is a נדר that
it doesn't all go away, that parts go away and parts could
remain.
כיצד? נדר מן הכלכלה. nadar min hakalkala. You took a vow that
everything in this basket is אסור assur? to me, or actually what
you literally said is the basket is אסור assur. to me, but
somehow we assume you meant everything in the basket. והיו בה בנות
שוח v'hayu bah benot shuach and there were these בנות שוח benot
shuach which are a certain type of what do you call of
either dates or figs, like a type of fig. Okay. ואמר v'amar
and you said one minute, אילו הייתי יודע שבנות שוח בתוכה ilu
hayiti yode'a shebenot shuach betocha had I known that there were figs,
לא הייתי נודר, lo hayiti noder, I never would have vowed, I
love figs. So in that case הכלכלה אסורה ובנות שוח מותרות. hakalkala
asura uvenot shuach mutarot. Okay. Therefore okay so the בנות שוח benot
shuach are excluded, everything else is אסור. assur, That's we don't say
הותר מקצתו הותר כולו. hutar miktzato hutar kulo That was the original
position. That was the חכמים. chachamim. עד שבא רבי עקיבא ולימד ad
sheba Rabbi Akiva velimeid until רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva. came along and
taught נדר שהותר מקצתו הותר כולו.
No it is totally permissible. So the גמרא says so okay another
example where according to רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva it's all permissible. So
let's guess what you hypothetically would have said. So the גמרא says
מאי לאו דאמר mai lav d'amar is it not a case that
you
said אילו הייתי יודע שבנות שוח בתוכה ilu hayiti yode'a shebenot shuach
betocha had I known that these figs are in it, הייתי אומר
hayiti omer תאנים שחורות ולבנות אסורות בנות שוח מותרות. te'einim shechorot ulevanot
asurot benot shuach mutarot. I would have identified the black ones and
the white ones are forbidden, the בנות שוח benot shuach are מותר
meaning isn't it a case where the alternative is that what you
would have done is you would have said a משנה דבריו. meshaneh
devarav. No not a qualifier, that's a משנה דבריו. meshaneh devarav You
wouldn't have said everything except for בנות שוח, benot shuach, you would
have said this and this and this and this is אסור assur.
but the בנות שוח benot shuach are מותר that you would have
been a משנה דבריו meshaneh devarav. not a מקיים דבריו. mekayem devarav.
And of course the bizarre thing is as תוספות Tosfot asks why
in the previous case about the onions do we say oh obviously
what he would have said hypothetically was he just would have added
a qualifier? Whereas here by the figs we said oh obviously what
he would have said is he would have totally been משנה דבריו.
meshaneh devarav.
לאו דווקא lav davka he wants to explore both possibilities.
I understand but it's funny that it phrases it as a question
to רבא Rava, and the answer in both cases is obvious. Who
told you what hypothetically he would have said? I'll tell you he
would have said hypothetically the position that fits my approach. Okay anyway
so the גמרא is assuming for some bizarre reason that in this
case what he would have said would not have been the same
statement with a qualifier but would have been an actual different statement,
a משנה דבריו. meshaneh devarav Okay and if that's true why are
the חכמים chachamim arguing on רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva according to you
רבא? Rava, You say when it's משנה דבריו meshaneh devarav? everybody agrees
it's okay. So the גמרא says ופליגי רבנן. ufeligi rabanan. So why
are the rabbis arguing? Why do they say the rest of the
figs are forbidden? Isn't it a case where you would have been
completely משנה דבריו? meshaneh devarav So the גמרא says well no who
told you that's what it would have been? באומר be'omer you say
אילו הייתי יודע שבנות שוח בתוכה ilu hayiti yode'a shebenot shuach betocha
had I known that there was those special figs in it, הייתי
אומר hayiti omer כל הכלכלה אסורה בנות שוח מותרות. kol hakalkala asura
benot shuach mutarot. I would have said the same statement with a
qualifier. Okay so basically these last two questions are directly relevant much
more than this whole case of the ראשון and אחרון. acharon. Okay
these are cases where one thing is, but how do you ask
questions from it? There's no evidence in these cases what hypothetically you
would have said. I'll just make it the case that hypothetically it
would have said the position that fits my approach. If I think
hypothetically it only worked if you make a radically different statement, if
it only worked if you would have hypothetically made a radically different
statement, that's what I'll say the case is. And if I say
that no, it releases the whole vow even if you would have
made a slightly different statement, that's what I'll say the case is.
Okay so now the גמרא wraps
up. מאן תנא להא דתנו רבנן? man tanna leha detanu rabanan? Who's
the תנא tanna of that which we taught?
נדר מחמישה בני אדם כאחד. nadar michamishah benei adam ke'echad. I said
from five people you're all forbidden, you know, you're all forbidden from
me, or I'm all forbidden or I'm forbidden from all of you,
whatever. Okay. הותר לאחד מהן הותרו כולן. hutar le'echad mehen hutru kullan.
If I was released from one of them then they're all permitted.
חוץ מאחד מהן chutz me'echad mehen if it was except for one
of them,
הוא מותר והן אסורין. hu mutar vehen asurin. He is permissible and
they are forbidden. So what does that mean? First it says when
you got released from one it all fell off. Then it says
except for one, that one is that one is excluded and the
rest are and the rest remain forbidden. So what's the difference right?
So the גמרא understands that the difference is actually these are two
separate תנאים, tannaim, that these are two separate opinions here. One is
the opinion of הותר מקצתו הותר כולו hutar miktzato hutar kulo. and
the other is the opinion of we don't say הותר מקצתו הותר
כולו. hutar miktzato hutar kulo. Okay do you see how the two
statements in this ברייתא baraita basically contradicts one another? Okay so the
גמרא says like this. אי לרבא רישא רבי עקיבא סיפא דברי הכל.
i l'Rava reisha Rabbi Akiva seifa divrei hakol. So for רבא Rava
the רישא reisha would be רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva that's הותר מקצתו
הותר כולו. hutar miktzato hutar kulo And the סיפא seifa is everybody.
When would we say everybody would agree that it would remain forbidden?
When it would be a case of מקיים mekayem. דבריו. Okay so
if it was a case of a radical משנה Mishna, דבריו that's
the רישא reisha הותר מקצתו הותר כולו according to רבי עקיבא. Rebbi
Akiva If it's a case of מקיים דברו, mekayem dvaro, then, right,
then according to דברי הכל, divrei hakol, would it still remain אסור?
assur, Is that am I losing people?
Right,
basically this ברייתא braita says you said כולם אסורים, kulam assurim, and
it basically had two statements. It says הותר לאחד מהם, hutar le'echad
mehem, okay? So basically it says, right, כולם מותר, kulam mutar, and
then it says חוץ מאחד, chutz mechad,
right, כולם אסורים, kulam assurim, except for that one, okay, except for
him, חוץ מאחד. chutz mechad. Okay, okay, חוץ מאחד. chutz mechad. So
what's the difference? Do we say הותרה מקצתה הותרה כולה hutra miktzata
hutra kula or do we not say הותרה מקצתה הותרה כולה? hutra
miktzata hutra kula? Which are we saying? So it says according to
רבה, Rabba here's the story. Remember רבה Rabba says when do we
say הותרה כולה? hutra kula? When it's משנה דברו, meshaneh dvaro, when
you would have said it completely different. So this statement that it's
כולם מותר kulam mutar is a case of משנה.
This statement where it remains אסור, assur, what's a case for רבה
Rabba. would say that even רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva. would say it
remains אסור? assur. מקיים. mekayem So this actually reads very nicely according
to רבה. Rabba, According to רבה, Rabba, this reads: if you would
have said a different statement, then they're all מותר. If you would
have said חוץ מאחד, chutz mechad, actually reads beautiful, the words חוץ
מאחד chutz mechad here means if you would have said the same
statement except for if you would have just added a qualifier, then
they remain אסור. So that this ברייתא braita reads beautifully according to
רבה, Rabba okay?
So okay, ורבה רישא רבי עקיבא סיפא דברי הכל, veRabba reisha Rebbi
Akiva seifa divrei hakol, of course then if even רבי עקיבא Rebbi
Akiva, says it's אסור, it's דברי הכל, divrei hakol, everybody says it's
אסור. ולרבא סיפא רבנן ורישא דברי הכל. uLeRava seifa rabanan ureisha divrei
hakol. According to רבא, Rava okay, the סיפא seifa here of חוץ
מאחד, chutz mechad, it's everybody agrees the difference is מקיים mekayem versus
משנה. The מקיים mekayem. is exactly the חוץ מאחד. chutz mechad. So
רבא Rava agrees that there's an opinion that says חוץ מאחד chutz
mechad that everybody else remains אסור, that's the non-רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva
position, right? That if you would have added a qualifier, it remains
אסור, that's the non-רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva position, okay? But רבא says
once you get to the stage of משנה דברו, meshaneh dvaro, then
everybody says that it's מותר. Yes? So according to רבא, this ברייתא
braita is רבנן rabanan who argue on רבי עקיבא. Rebbi Akiva. The
רבנן rabanan who argue on רבי עקיבא, Rebbi Akiva, they say when
you are מקיים דברו, mekayem dvaro, it still remains okay, but they
concede to רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva that when you're משנה דברו, meshaneh
dvaro, everybody is it's all מותר. So according to רבא, this whole
ברייתא braita is the רבנן, rabanan, they reject. רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva
says it's always מותר, even מקיים. mekayem But the רבנן rabanan say,
no, it's משנה it's מותר, מקיים it's אסור. And רבה Rabba says
this whole ברייתא braita is רבי עקיבא. Rebbi Akiva So the difference
between this ברייתא braita is probably why you have the whole discussion
of רבה Rabba and רבא, why you introduced, where did we get
this crazy idea to introduce the idea that it matters hypothetically what
you would have hypothetically said, right? Where do we see any evidence
of that? So the only place we see evidence is we have
this ברייתא braita that says הותר לאחד כולם מותרים חוץ מאחד כולם
אסורים. hutar le'echad kulam mutarim chutz mechad kulam assurim. What the heck?
The same thing! So they say no, no, חוץ מאחד chutz mechad
means you would have said the same statement with a qualifier. So
here you see when you would have said the same statement with
a qualifier, it's more of a problem. And then the whole debate
of רבה Rabba and רבא is who's this ברייתא braita going like?
Is this ברייתא braita going like רבי עקיבא, Rebbi Akiva that even
רבי עקיבא only said his position when you're משנה דברו? meshaneh dvaro?
That's what רבה Rabba says. And רבא says no, the ברייתא braita
is going like the רבנן. rabanan. The רבנן rabanan will say that
when you say a qualifier it's no good, okay? And but they
would admit that when it was משנה דברו meshaneh dvaro it would
be good. רבי עקיבא would say it would always be good. Okay,
so this ברייתא braita is the hinges is where that debate came
from and it's according to רבה it's רבי עקיבא and according to
רבא it's the רבנן. rabanan.
Yes? I have two questions. You're saying that the redactor of the
בבלי Bavli
took
a משנה, took this תוספתא, Tosefta, put this תוספתא Tosefta at the
end of the סוגיא sugya and then can link the two conceptually
with the debate in between.
Right. I mean it's true.
It's a phenomenal literary right.
I mean it's phenomenal,
it's pretty wild.
Right, I mean you could have constructed this completely differently. You could
have said, starting with the ברייתא braita and said מאי שנא רישא
ומאי שנא סיפא. mai shna reisha u'mai shna seifa. And then you
would have said well, no, it remains what hypothetically you would say
and is this רבי עקיבא and is this רבנן? rabanan? But anyway,
that's definitely how I see it. I see it.